SuhasUpadhye

571-344-9123 | Washington, DC | suhasu@gmail.com | https://www.linkedin.com/in/suhas-cloud-sme

Professional Summary

A SME of multiple cloud environments with over 15 years of experience who has worked with measurable deliverables, in a 24x7 production environment. Possess enterprise solution architecture experience in AWS, Azure, Oracle Cloud, and GCP cloud environments. Expert level experience working with data such as Data Marts, Data Governance, Data Migration and Application Integration. Self-motivated, efficient, and highly technical with hands-on experience in cloud architecture, cloud migration, cloud governanceall comprising large databases with high transaction volumes.

Professional Experience

Bank of America
Enterprise Azure Solutions Architect SME

05/2021 - Current

- Led a team responsible for Data Synapse/Azure Synapse + analytics, Data warehouse/ Data migration and building out proof of concept in the cloud to handle 10+ Petabytes of data across multiple LOB's.
- Azure Cybersecurity admin, MS Defender for Cloud, Regulatory Compliances, NIST-800-53, etc.
- Supporting security tests and evaluations (ST&Es); creating Plans of Action and Milestones (POA&Ms); conducting FISMA self-assessments; conducting system security assessments.
- Collaborated with Microsoft / Azure consultants and CDO trusted data fabric team to ensure bank security and data governance standards are supported by new Data Warehouse service on Azure.
- Conducting system security planning; developing security policies & procedures; and providing security documentation support based on NIST SP-800-53 and DHS 4300 guidelines. Work with Privacy Information and Personally Identifiable Information (PII) data.
- Configuring Azure Virtual machines, Resource Manager, Service Fabric, Container Service, SQL Database,
 Virtual Network, DNS, Azure Active Directory and Azure Kubernetes Services incl. Docker containers.
- Implemented security using Active Directory and VPNs, strong authentication and single sign-on with digital certificates.
- Involved in design, implementation and modifying Infrastructure.

Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation (FDIC) Cloud Architect - Azure Infrastructure/ Azure Security SME

02/2021 - 05/2021

- Set up Azure infrastructure, Cloud assessment and Cloud migration.
- Collaborated with other architects on the program to devise solutions for complex technical capabilities
- Researched and integrated system architecture strategies, product specifications, development schedules, and user expectations into product capabilities.
- Researched emerging technologies to determine impact on application execution.
- Created Data Factories in Azure Data Factory (ADF), transforming data with ADF Transformations as well as Monitoring, producing & consuming data dets of ADF.
- Provided technical guidance and work leadership to engineers.
- Developed PowerShell, Python and shell scripts for resource provisioning & automation.
- Worked as an escalation point for operational and technical items related to Azure.
- Drove and Lead Troubleshooting call for Azure services.
- Conducted extensive Vulnerability and Penetration Testing Assessments on Web Based Application and Infrastructure Penetration Testing.
- Port/Vulnerability Scanning: Nmap/Nmap Scripting Engine (NSE), Netcat, Nessus.

- Translated technical knowledge and skills into real business conversations, solution-selling, and talents with the BD executives to create proposals and new initiatives.
- Responsible for defining the overall solution design of the project, covering all layers of the architecture: business, information and technical.
- Architect "To-Be" technology platform for data lake build and analytics workbench.
- Development of Hybrid Cloud Strategy by using knowledge of current state and a future vision of public and private cloud technologies as benefits the needs of the client.
- Identified research opportunities in line with the business and IT strategy and proposed innovative solutions.
- Snowflake Cloud Data Platform POC implementation and comparison with Azure Datalake / Synapse Analytics, AWS DataLake / Redshift, and Informatica Cloud iPaaS. AWS CloudEndure migration POC.
- Acted as the design authority for assigned projects and programs throughout implementation in alignment with architecture governance.

Government IT Program: Federal Communications Commission (FCC) Solution Architect / Cloud Data Architect

12/2019 - 2/2020

- Implementing Cloud Solutions using various AWS.
- Developed and implemented Azure Resource Manager (ARM) and Terraform templates and scripting tools, including PowerShell, Azure CLI and Shell scripts.
- Design & architect batch / near real time ingestion-based data architecture and strategy to support successful business data transformation & migration on AWS.
- Lift and shift of an existing on-premises application to AWS.
- Selecting the appropriate AWS service based on data, compute, database, or security requirements.
- Developed strategies for data acquisitions/ETL

Government IT Program: U.S. Internal Revenue Service (IRS) Cloud Data Architect

02/2016 - 11/2019

- Providing Database support to a large-scale Modernization of the US Federal government's IRS Tax Information Systems.
- Analyzing and implementing Database requirements and accomplishing proof of concepts.
- Performing Oracle database Subject Matter Expertise (SME) and best practices in the enhancement of IRS database systems of the Affordable Care Act (ACA).
- Aiding Data as a Service (DaaS), Data Security, Data Extraction, Data Transformation, and transitioning to a Web-based Business Management Information Systems (BMIS), leveraging EPD data received by CDR from CMS via IS&R system.
- Research into problems with existing application design and develop long term solutions.
- Responsible for Planning, Analysis, Design, and Implementation of Infrastructure components for an Enterprise Operational Data Store (ODS) and Data Warehouse (EDW).
- Analyze detail systems factors: input/output requirements, information flow, hardware and software requirements, alternative approaches, etc.
- Analyze problems. propose alternative solutions and criteria that allow deciding on which approach to take, and proceed with the most optimal choice.
- Implemented multiple replication sites for Oracle migration project using GoldenGate Software to migrate five multiple terabyte enterprise Oracle 11g to AWS RDS Oracle databases on Sun Solaris UNIX platform with minimal downtime.
- Developed automated tests that can be incorporated into Continuous Integration / Continuous Delivery (CI/CD) pipeline.
- Supported CI/CD initiatives and utilize static code analyzers to ensure high quality source code.

02/2013 - 04/2016

- Oracle GoldenGate12c Replication
- Organized replication strategy in an Oracle/SqlServer environment that included 3 ORACLE 10g/11g RAC environments and 48 Distributed SqlServer databases. Replicating real-time from three primary ORACLE DB's to array of SqlServer with primary and secondary switchover.
- Install/configure/support Oracle GoldenGate data replication. Resolve replication conflicts. Troubleshoot GoldenGate performance issues.
- Install/configure/support Oracle GoldenGate on UNIX, performance tune slow replication.
- Configure Oracle GoldenGate on MS SQL server and Oracle databases.
- Install/configure/support Oracle GoldenGate Monitor Server, configure monitoring, tune performance issues.
- Configure Oracle Transparent Gateway to allow connections between Oracle databases and MS Sql server.
- Installation and Configuration Oracle GoldenGate Veridata and compare the data online.
- Migration of application-code for Version upgrade from Oracle 10g/11gR2 to AWS Oracle RDS.
- Migration of Informatica replication solution to Oracle GoldenGate 11gR2 and 12c

CollegeBoard 02/2005 – 06/2006

Cloud Solution Architect / Oracle SME

Keane Inc. 01/1996 – 01/2005

Cloud Data Architect / Sr. DBA/ GoldenGate Architect

Certifications

Microsoft Azure Certifications

Azure Cybersecurity Architect Expert

Azure Solutions Architect Expert

Azure Al Fundamentals

Identity and Access Administrator Associate

Azure Data Engineer Associate

Security Operations Analyst

Azure Administrator Associate

Azure Al Fundamentals

Azure Data Fundamentals

Azure Fundamentals

Azure Network Engineer Associate Security, Compliance, and Identity Fundamentals

Azure Security Engineer Associate

Google Cloud Platform Certification

GCP Professional Cloud Engineer GCP Associate Cloud Engineer GCP Cloud Digital Leader

Amazon Web Services Certifications

Amazon Web Services (AWS) Certified AWS - Certified Solutions Architect Associate (CSA)

AWS Certified SysOps Administrator - Associate (CSO) AWS - Certified Cloud Practitioner (CCP)

Oracle Cloud Certifications

Oracle Cloud Infrastructure (OCI) Certified OCI Certified Architect Associate OCI Certified Architect Professional OCI Foundations Certified Associate

Databricks Certification

Databricks Certified -Fundamentals of Databricks Lakehouse Platform

Education

Mumbai University | Mumbai
 Bachelor of Engineering – Manufacturing

I.I. T | Mumbai
 Master's Degree in Engineering -Technology